spf13.com stevefrancia.com twitter.com/spf13 github.com/spf13

# Executive • Leader • Advocate • Engineer

I'm a product focused technology executive with strategic, technical and operational experience from companies including Google, Docker, and MongoDB in dev ops, software development, product development, community building, and program management and the proven ability to build and lead large global heterogenous teams. I have been responsible for the #1 most wanted database by developers (MongoDB) and the #1 language developers want to learn (Go). I'm a globally recognized thought leader across a variety of industries including cloud, open source, developer advocacy, developer experience, big data, database, and language design.

# **Summary**

**Executive management** 17 years of executive management experience establishing high-growth businesses, fast growth efficient technology teams and organization alignment in cloud, open source and database.

**Open source** Leader responsible for **5 of the "Top 100" open source projects** (Go, Docker, Hugo, MongoDB, Drupal). Creator of many open source projects with broad adoption and vibrant contributor & user communities.

**Technology expertise** 22 years of experience as an architect, dev ops leader, software engineer, program manager, architect, product lead, UI / UX lead, DBA and system operator.

**Entrepreneur** Member of leadership teams responsible for building two "unicorns" (+\$1B valuation) from very early stages. VPE/CTO at 4 NYC based startups. Founder of successful custom development & consulting firm. Advisor to multiple companies.

Industry leader Keynote & featured speaker at over 30 international conferences. O'Reilly author. Conference & summit organizer.

# **Experience**

Product Lead - Go Language, Google; NYC — 2016 - Present Responsible for strategy, product, developer relations, user experience & ecosystem

Go is an open-source programming language created at Google with a user base of 1.5M+ developers and has become the foundation for cloud applications and infrastructure including Dropbox, Docker and Kubernetes.

- Responsible for user adoption including branding and marketing for the Go project resulting in significant industry adoption, 400%+ acceleration in adoption (15% → 65% annual growth rate), and recognition as a top 5 most loved and wanted language.
- Wrote the story of "the value of Go" and how it is a strategic asset to Google. Presented to Google senior management securing an 30% increase of investment in Go.
- One of six members of the technical leadership team responsible for determining the technical direction of the Go language, especially Go 2.
- Responsible for the worldwide Go ecosystem including over 1.5M+ users, 1000s of contributors and companies, 100s of meet ups and conferences, etc.
- Responsible for the Go user experience resulting in significant refinements to documentation, websites, installation, training, etc. including reducing Go installation time from ~30 minutes to ~2 minutes
- Performed a complete rewrite of the Go contributor experience including rewriting the contributor guide, refining the contributor workflow, creating a contributor workshop and establishing a mentorship program resulting in 60% increase in contributions YoY.
- Restructured the project organization and governance to expand leadership beyond Google via working groups.
- Reimagined user feedback and greatly expanded it via user surveys and questionnaires (over 8k responders), user feedback sessions and establishing a program for dedicated user communication for critical adopters.
- Authoring playbook for Google-wide adoption on running a successful open source ecosystem.
- Defining metrics used across Google on evaluating open source project health and growth.
- Led the creation and adoption of Google's open source code of conduct and it's enforcement across open source.

  Met with external industry leaders to drive adoption.

spf13.com stevefrancia.com twitter.com/spf13 github.com/spf13

## Chief Operator, Docker; SF, CA - 2014 - 2015

Revolutionizing the way distributed applications are built, shipped, and run.

Responsible for open source strategy & operations, core engineering, dev ops, and documentation

Brought on to guide the company through a period of explosive growth and adoption. During my time on the leadership team the company headcount grew 3x, sales and valuation grew 10x while Docker became the fastest adopted technology in history with over 500M downloads in it's first 24 months.

- Responsible for the fastest growing and one of the largest developer communities in open source with over 1300 developers from Docker, Microsoft, Google, IBM, RedHat, Huawei, HP, CoreOS, Rackspace, etc.
- ▶ Led the core engineering team responsible for docker & libContainer (now moby & runc/containerd).
- Responsible for reversing declining active open source contributors resulting in over 300% increase.
- Led a rewrite of the Docker developer experience including expanding the contributor guide & documentation and refining the contributor workflow with automation, improved tooling & continuous integration testing.
- Guided Docker's participation in establishing the Open Container Initiative & Cloud Native Computing Foundation.
- ▶ Restructured the governance of the Docker project and led the Docker Governance Advisory Board.
- Devised and successfully executed the world's first open-source-a-thon with over 1000 developers participating in 26 events around the world resulting in over 300 contributions.
- Responsible for technical writing, software licensing and compliance across Docker.

# Chief Developer Advocate/VP Engineering, MongoDB; NYC, NY — 2011 - 2014 Company behind MongoDB, the market leading disruptive NoSQL database.

Responsible for the MongoDB developer experience, open source strategy & evangelism

Responsible for building out and leading a developer experience engineering department from scratch. Hired and led over 75 engineers, technical writers, systems engineers, and managers including 7 VPs/Directors. During my time on the leadership team the company grew 12x, sales grew 40x, valuation grew 40x while MongoDB became the 4th most popular database and the leading NoSQL database. Maintained single digit attrition rates across my staff.

#### **ENGINEERING**

- Hired and led a distributed engineering team developing drivers, libraries & integrations in over 12 languages (C, C#, C++, Java, Ruby, Python, PHP, Node, Scala, Go, Perl & more) with personalities as varied as the languages.
- Frew the team from 0 to 30 engineers in 3 years while providing critical leadership at each stage including the promotion and mentoring of 4 engineers to lead/director/VP roles.
- Led the design & specification of the MongoDB User Interface considered to be a defining feature of MongoDB.
- Responsible for external integrations including Hadoop, HDFS, AWS, Azure, Storm, Spark & Drupal.

#### **ADVOCACY, PROGRAM MANAGEMENT & COMMUNITY**

- Established the MongoDB Masters program with over 50 community leaders and bi-annual summit.
- Worked with many open source communities and commercial partners to establish a broad ecosystem of drivers, libraries and tools supporting MongoDB.
- ▶ Established and led industry leading developer advocacy efforts of 90+ speakers at 160+ unique events annually.
- Developed messaging, core curriculum and presentations for over 40 different MongoDB conferences.

#### **DOCUMENTATION**

- Established and led technical writing team responsible for all documentation, specs, and technical writing.
- Oversaw complete rewrite of documentation from a wiki based system to an industry leading documentation manual with over 1000 pages with translations in multiple languages.

#### **WEB & TOOLS**

- Led engineering for 10gen.com/mongodb.com utilizing Drupal 7 with a MongoDB backend resulting in considerable contributions to Drupal 7 & 8.
- Responsible for MongoDB.org with over 500k monthly views on the download page alone.
- Led tools engineering team responsible for creating tools to facilitate rapid growth of 30 to ~500 employees in 3 years.

spf13.com stevefrancia.com twitter.com/spf13 github.com/spf13

## VP Engineering, OpenSky; NYC, NY - 2010 - 2011

Social E-commerce providing personalized shopping experiences curated by friends, experts, and celebrities.

#### Responsible for all technology, development, and architecture

- Invented, patented and led implementation of world's first distributed (widgetized) checkout.
- Guided engineering through challenging company pivot. Led development of new business model while keeping team motivated & focused through major rewrite.
- Rapidly hired diverse engineering team taking team from 3 engineers to 15 within first 3 months while defining culture leading OpenSky to be on Crain's "Best Places to Work in NYC 2010" list in it's first year of operation.
- Led OpenSky to become a contributor to many open source projects including Symfony2, Doctrine, MongoODM, MongoDB, Mule and HornetMQ.
- Partnered with the product team to create a clear and cohesive vision and translated that vision into a scalable fully distributed e-commerce platform built using PHP 5.3, Symfony2, Doctrine 2, Twig, jQuery, Mule ESB, HornetMQ and MongoDB launching ahead of schedule facilitating explosive growth from 10k members through 250k in first 3 months (averaging over 3k signups per day).
- Engineered PCI compliant e-commerce flash sale platform including full order management system, analytics & data warehouse with integration of hundreds of drop ship vendors and 3PL facility and NetSuite.

## CIO & COO, VP Technology, Portero; NYC, NY — 2007 - 2010

Portero is the leading authentic luxury marketplace for new and vintage luxury items.

## Responsible for product, technology and operations while managing a staff of 100+

- Led company through major pivot corresponding with financial downturn of 2008 by conceiving and implementing a platform based strategy. Raised **\$6.6M** in **funding** on the basis of the new strategy.
- Launched three products: Portero Private, Portero.com and Portero's Vendor Platform ahead of time and under budget, taking from conception through successful launch and beyond while keeping ahead of substantial growth (over 500% increase within 6 months) leveraging open source technologies, including Magento & Drupal 6.
- Restructured operations department and processes reducing inventory processing time from 3 weeks to 3 days and reducing costs by 40%. Renegotiated existing IT contracts resulting in 30% cost savings annually.
- Architected redundant, scalable, secure and PCI compliant infrastructure.

#### VP Development, Takkle [Acq. Alloy]; NYC, NY — 2006 - 2007

TAKKLE is the first online social network for sports, one place for all amateur athletes, coaches and fans.

#### Responsible for product and technology

- Successfully grew, mentored and led development team acting as architect, manager and lead developer taking
   Takkle.com from a concept to over 1M registered users (over 250k users in first year).
- Acted as thought partner communicating technical possibilities, timing and challenges to the business as well building and unifying the development centered around the business goals delivering all projects on time and feature complete
- Oversaw integration of Akamai's CDN, DoubleClick, Omniture and LinkShare.

#### Founder & President, Supernerd; Provo, UT — 2001 - 2007

Technology consulting and development firm focused on applying emerging technologies with a focus on open source to a wide range of challenges facing businesses and higher education.

- Created Supersite, a multilingual content management and e-commerce SAAS product using PHP, MySQL / PostgreSQL, Javascript, HTML and CSS.
- Installed and maintained a fully heterogeneous data center providing hosting and statewide DSL connectivity.
- Chief architect and principle author of the Zoop Framework, the first object oriented framework for PHP.

#### **CLIENTS** (representative sample)

Brigham Young University - Developed curriculum and taught university course on creating web applications

Priceline.com - Implemented Priceline's first affiliate program (white label).

Real Salt Lake (Major League Soccer) - Developed pioneering hybrid physical & online digital media guide.

Toyota - Develop a prototype driver media/GPS interface for Lexus models.

spf13.com stevefrancia.com twitter.com/spf13 github.com/spf13

## Sr Developer & Project Manager, Medialink [acq. Cision]; Norwalk, CT — 2001

A global leader in providing unique news and marketing media strategies and solutions.

Figure 1 Engineered solution unifying data gathering and analytics across 8 worldwide locations using ASP and MSSQL.

### DBA, Mercedes Benz Financial; Norwalk, CT — 1998

A division of DaimlerChrysler, the preferred finance provider for Mercedes-Benz dealers and their customers.

Responsible for creation and maintenance of databases for US based Mercedes, Fleetwood & Sterling dealerships.

## Senior Systems Administrator, American Telecom; Norwalk, CT — 1995 - 1998

Large regional ISP during the pioneer days of the internet.

- Played key role in a fast growing ISP in the earliest days of the public internet.
- Project manager in building one of the first e-commerce stores for an international luggage company, (ebags).
- Installed and managed primary data center using Microsoft and Unix (Solaris, DigitalUX, BSD and Linux) systems on various architectures.

## Education

▶ Brigham Young University, Provo UT — BA

# **Board Memberships & Open Source Leadership**

#### **Board of Directors**

- Drupal Association
- wRank Inc

## **Advisory Board**

- Docker
- Rhone Apparel
- CoreOS
- Broadway Video Ventures

# Engineering, Ecosystem & Project Leadership

Creator, architect & leader of many of the most popular libraries, applications & frameworks in open source

- Moby (formerly Docker) 48k ★'s 1700 Contributors Container framework
- Go 38k ★'s 1000 Contributors Go programming language
- > Drupal 100k+ Contributors Enterprise CMS powering whitehouse.gov, teslamotors.com, harvard.edu, etc
- ► Hugo 24k ★'s 500 Contributors Fast static website content engine powering labs.usa.gov, smashingmagazine.com, developer.atlassian.com & millions more
- MongoDB 13k ★'s 300 Contributors NoSQL Distributed Database
- **Spf13-vim** − 12k ★'s − 130 Contributors − The most popular Vim distribution
- Cobra 7k ★'s 135 Contributors Framework for CLI applications in Go used by over 400 applications including Kubernetes, Dropbox, Git LFS, Docker, OpenShift, etcd, rkt, RedHat's Project Atomic

#### **Community Leadership**

Organizer & MC of many different community events

- Co-organizer of GopherCon & GothamGo with a combined 2k attendees annually.
- Responsible for the definitive example of how to deal with trolls in open source communities (according to S.O.).
- Organizer of many hack-a-thons, meetups, birds of a feather sessions & developer summits internationally.
- Instrumental in developing a Google-wide Code of Conduct & enforcement guide.

#### Industry Leadership

Thought leader presenting at dozens of international developer conferences

- ▶ Keynote or featured speaker at LinuxCon, OSCON, Strata, Strangeloop, GopherCon, GopherFest, GothamGo, MongoDB, DockerCon, Big Data Paris, Hack + Startup, DrupalCon, RootsTech, SORT, SINFO and many more.
- Crafted over 30 unique presentations with over 700k views.
- Participant in working groups defining architecture, governance, etc for Go, Docker, MongoDB, Drupal and more.
- ▶ Author of one of the "best programming blogs" according to Quora with 30k+ monthly visitors